A Guide to the Lee-Jackson Collection: An Informal Guide to its Highlights as Perceived by Betty Kondayan, August 1992
Special Collections, Washington and Lee University
Special Collections, Leyburn Library, Washington and Lee University
Lee-Jackson Collection
Special Collections, Leyburn Library, Washington and Lee University
170
This collection, given to Washington and Lee in 1989 by the Lee-Jackson Foundation of Charlottesville, Va. consists of ca. 118 items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
Robert E. Lee, 1807-1870
The sixteen R.E. Lee items (11 of them ALS) cover a date span of 22 years - from 1847 through 1869. A number are perfunctory, but two letters seemed to me extremely interesting. The first, written aboard the Ship Massachusetts off Lobos, Mexico, on 28 February 1847, during the Mexican War to "My dear Major," contains a beautiful description of Tampico and the natural riches Lee saw there. He is enthusiastic about the fruit, vegetables, and fish in the market and about having seen chocolate growing. "In fact I was charmed with Tampico, & if it depends upon my vote, it will never fall back to Mexico." He also describes Lobos Island, the coral reef around it, and the rubber tree he has been. "It is the most remarkable growth I have even seen."
His letter of 8 September 1865 to Matthew Fontaine Maury who was in Mexico attempting to establish a settlement there after the Confederate defeat, is beautifully expressed. In it he makes very clear that he feels it is best for ex-Confederates to stay in the United States and attempt to heal wounds and build, rather than to leave in despair. Yet he writes to Maury (and in an earlier letter to Richard Maury, Matthew's son) without judgment for the step Maury has taken. Again he expresses his admiration for Mexico. "The salubrity of its climate, the fertility of its soil, & the magnificence of its scenery, possess for me great charms, but I look with delight upon the mountains & rivers of my native State still." He realizes that those ex-Confederates in Mexico are profiting from Maury's presence, "but I shall be very sorry if your presence be lost to Virginia." She has now need for all her sons, and can ill afford to spare you."
Mary Randolph Custis Lee, 1808-1873
There are 10 ALS of Mrs. Lee ranging from the early 1850s in Baltimore to shortly before her death in Lexington in 1873. Although Mrs. Lee's handwriting is extremely hard to decipher and most of her letters are undated, I found her letters the most interesting group in the collection with the possible exception of those of her father, George Washington Parke Custis. One reason for this is that Mrs. Lee's personality shines through clearly ' and it is not always as charming as her father's. Yet one feels she is very real, very human.
In one of several letters to Benson Lossing who helped her publish G.W.P. Custis's book on Washington, she vents her anger at former slaves in what would now be regarded as very racist remarks. She expresses bitterness over the loss of Arlington, over Grant's being on the presidential ticket, and about the fact that her poor health prevents her from going out into the green spring or on a trip to Europe. In a letter appended to an affectionate note from Rooney (about 15 at the time) to Custis at West Point, she needles her eldest son about his backwardness with women and worries over the state of his studies. She reminds him to read his Bible - and quotes "Aunt Lewis" as saying "she can give you no better advice than to follow in your Father's footsteps."
Mrs. Lee has lively details about the various spas she went to and gossip about the flirtations of the young. She also mentions her painting, a talent she apparently inherited from her father.
George Washington Parke Custis, 1781-1857
The Seven ALS of Mrs. Lee's father (and George Washington's step-grandson) were a delightful surprise. A man of many interests (farming, theatre, painting), his charm emerges in most of his communications. An especially enlightening and colorful letter is that of 16 September 1839 to his wife and daughter who were away on a visit. In it he describes the activities at Arlington, the crops, the animals, the repairs to the house, the servants, and reports that "I have an increase of piggy wiggys..." He speaks of partridges and poachers, peaches and quince. The quality of his wool is good - and he has seen fit to send "two Beets, one squash to the Horticultural Exhibition."
Another interesting letter is to the Honorable Henry Wise who was apparently exploring the possibility of establishing a bathing facility. Custis, who had inherited Smith's Island, tries to persuade Wise to consider that island, where there would not only be good bathing but good wild mutton, fishing, shooting, "egging," and lots of timber. He thinks that a Southern resort would have various advantages over Cape May, Saratoga, and Newport.
His letter to Benson Lossing, 2 December 1855, discusses his plays and the large battle scenes he loved to paint.
The Lee Girls
There is only one letter from Agnes (1841-1873), but it is affecting in its hints about her feeling of loneliness and isolation in Lexington (14 January 1867).
Four letters from Mildred (1846-1905), all expressive of her personality, are in the collection. To Matthew Maury (M. F. Maury's grandson who was Mildred's godson), she wrote on 4 January 1874 a poignant note thanking him for a cross he had sent which she has placed on Agnes' grave. An undated early letter to Preston Cocke has a flirtatious tone. Although she turns him down for a ride (it is too hot), she praises his poetic bent. In another undated letter from London to "Mary," she says she hates the city and longs for trees and grass.
The Lee Boys
One of the letters I liked most from a Lee Boy was a R.E. Lee, Jr.'s to Capt. Edmund R. Cocke (14 January 1866) in which he says if any woman will build him a house he'll marry her. Also: "I came within an inch of having a chill, but a kind friend took me in to the bar (concerned you know) & we both took the 'bath' hot strong & some sugar & emon in it which turned my liver from its vile intentions." After signing his name he adds: "formerly Lt. C.S.A. (& so called at large) & now an Esquire dwelling in the wildest wilds of the loneliest corner of King William Co. said co. being the loneliest of the lonely."
William Henry Fitzhugh Lee's boyhood letter to his brother Custis from Baltimore on February 15, 1852 has been mentioned. William Henry Fitzhugh or "Rooney" was 15 at the time. In an affectionate, lively letter, perhaps intended to cheer up his sober elder brother, Rooney does his best to cover the important news. Washington Lewis, who has been visiting, is to be married to a woman Rooney "beleave[s]" to be not very pretty though very good. He himself is going to go to dancing school "to learn to trip it." Uncle Smith is off to sea; Rooney is beginning Horace and reading Xenephon in Greek. If Custis's spirits were raised by Rooney's note, they were soon to be dampened by his mother's which was appended (see above).
Custis's own letters which display the best handwriting of all the Lees are nevertheless probably the dullest in the collection (though Fitzhugh Lee's run them a close second). And Fitzhugh's handwriting was terrible! After the war, Fitzhugh, Lee's nephew, was obsessed with land deals and taxes; and his correspondence bears witness to this. Most of the letters here are to his cousin and attorney, Charlie Kerr, in Baltimore.
Dates for the Lee Boys are as follows:
George Washington Custis 1832-1913
William Henry Fitzhugh (Rooney): 1837-1891
Robert Edward Jr. 1843-1914
Fitzhugh (nephew of General Lee): 1835- 1905
The Older Lees
Francis Lightfoot Lee (1734-97), Richard Henry Lee's brother (see Lee Family tree) and like him prominent at the time of the Revolution, is represented in the collection by a loving letter to "My dearest," no doubt hi wife, Rebecca Tayloe.
Richard Henry (1733-94) reports in a letter of 2 August 1781 to "your excellency" two deserters from the Continental army, the McKenny brothers. "They have twice deserted and are bad men." Another letter (21 October 1778) is addressed to Patrick Henry, governor of Virginia, and concerns the means of "paying the arrears due to the Continental Soldiers in Virginia and to the Militia of that State..."
Robert E. Lee's brother, Charles Carter Lee (1798-1871), in two letters to his cousin Nat Burwell, expresses his anxiety about his brother Robert's impending return from the Mexican War. "The Officers returned from Mexico all say that Robert's is the most enviable reputation in the army..." And "I have attended the arrival of the Southern cars for the last three mornings in hopes to see Robert get out of them, but have been disappointed, & now fear he has taken the route up the Mississippi. However, it is a great gratification to see that he has arrived safely in the country."
The Lee Associates
General Beauregard's and General J. E. Johnston's letters were interesting to me because of their letterheads which gave an indication of how some Confederates got involved in post-war businesses.
Perhaps the most interesting letter in the "associates" group is from Benjamin Hallowell (1799-1877), who was Robert E. Lee's tutor in Alexandria in 1824. This letter, written from Sandy Spring, Md. In 1873 to his cousin Robert Miller, gives a detailed account of the history of Alexandria's water supply and the establishment of a waterworks there in the 1850's. Beautifully expressed in an old-fashioned style, he outlines how one can move men forward towards a worthy project. When taking up a subscription for the waterworks, he prompted the wealthy citizens to give large amounts by giving generously himself. "The effect was Electric. I, a poor man, going so far beyond the wealthy ones, gave éclat to the subject." In graphic and interesting detail, he discusses the choosing of Frederick Erdman, an engineer who had successfully completed waterworks for Harrisburg, Pa. And Frederick, Md., for the job in Alexandria, and also relates how many of the problems in the project were overcome.
Another charming letter is that of 30 January 1873 from the Staunton, Va. Cartographer, Jed Hotchkiss, to his wife, from London. Besides telling her what he has bought for her, he gives instructions about the work his men should do while he is away, and explains why he has been delayed. "I feel quite confident of the financial result of my trip and that I shall soon be able to do better for you my dear, dear one than I have ever had it in my power to do before."
Final mention will be made of Margaret Junkin Preston (1820-1897). Two letters in the collection that were written before her marriage are to Mr. Sartain, a magazine publisher whom she wants to persuade to accept her writings. For a mid-19th century young Lexington woman, she shows a surprisingly practical, business-like approach and assertiveness.
Contents List
- Robert E. Lee to "My dear Major", written aboard Ship Massachusetts, Off Lobos 28 Feb. 1847, ALS (Box-folder 1:1)
- Robert E. Lee to Gen. Joseph G. Totten, from U.S. Military Academy, West Point 6 Jan. 1853, ALS (Box-folder 1:2)
- Robert E. Lee to Col. Clarke, from Headquarters, Sewell Mt. 11 Oct. 1861, ALS (Box-folder 1:3)
- Robert E. Lee, received in Staunton, to Major Harman, from Richmond 18 April 1862, Telegram (Box-folder 1:4)
- Robert E. Lee to "My dear Madam" from Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia near Martinsburg 23 Sept. 1862, letter in handwriting of Charles S. Venable, Lee's aide (Box-folder 1:5)
- Robert E. Lee to General Trimble 21 March 1863, ALS fragment (Box-folder 1:6)
- Robert E. Lee to His Excellency Governor John Letcher from Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia 31 Oct. 1863, LS (Box-folder 1:7)
- Robert E. Lee to Lt. General Ewell from Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia (written in pencil; appears to all be in Lee's handwriting). 10 May 1864, ADS or LS (Box-folder 1:8)
- Robert E. Lee to Mrs. Margaret B. Daingerfield from Near Petersburg 1 March 1865, ALS (Box-folder 1:9)
- Robert E. Lee to Col. Richard S. Maury from Near Cartersville 31 July 1865, ALS (Box-folder 1:10)
- Robert E. Lee (circular letter) from Near Cartersville 31 July 1865, LS (or possibly ALS) (Box-folder 1:11)
- Robert E. Lee to M. F. Maury from Near Cartersville 8 Sept. 1865, ALS (Box-folder 1:12)
- Robert E. Lee to Richard S. Maury from Near Cartersville 11 Sept. 1865, ALS (Box-folder 1:13)
- Robert E. Lee to Major W. I. Hawks from Lexington, Va. 8 Jan. 1866, ALS (Box-folder 1:14)
- Robert E. Lee to John W. Truslow from Lexington, Va. 7 March 1868, ALS (Box-folder 1:15)
- Robert E. Lee to Dr. A. G. Bledsoe from Lexington, Va. 15 May 1869, ALS (Box-folder 1:16)
- Printed funeral announcement re Robert E. Lee 15 Oct. 1870 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Agnes Lee to Mrs. Richard L. Maury from Lexington 14 Jan. 1867, ALS (Box-folder 1:18)
- Alfred Lee to N. Burwell 10 Feb. 1852 and N.D., 2 ALS (Box-folder 1:19)
- Arthur Lee court copy of his will made on 7 July 1792 26 Aug. 1803 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Arthur Lee printed copy of his An Appeal to the Justice and Interests of the People of Great Britain, in the Present Disputes with America1775 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Charles Lee to Joseph Nourse? From Alexandria 10 Oct. 1791, ALS (Box-folder 1:22)
- Charles Lee to James McHenry from Alexandria 28 Nov. 1801, ALS (Box-folder 1:23)
- Charles Lee to William A. Washington 28 Nov. 1802, DS (Box-folder 1:24)
- Charles Carter Lee to Nat Burwell from Richmond 1 Feb. 1848, ALS (Box-folder 1:25)
- Charles Carter Lee to Nat Burwell from Richmond 25 June 1848, ALS (Box-folder 1:26)
- Charlotte W. Lee to Nat Burwell from Arlington 30 April (N.D.), ALS (Box-folder 1:27)
- Edmund Jennings Lee to Alexander Brown from Philadelphia 11 Oct. 1892, ALS (Box-folder 1:28)
- Edmund Jennings Lee to Alexander Brown from Philadelphia 22 Oct. 1892, ALS (Box-folder 1:29)
- Edmund Jennings Lee to "My dear Sir" from Philadelphia 30 Dec. 1892, ALS (Box-folder 1:30)
- Francis Lightfoot Lee to "My dearest" from Richmond 5 July 1780, ALS (Box-folder 1:31)
- Fitzhugh Lee to "General" from Ravensworth 30 Sept. 1865, ALS (Box-folder 1:32)
- Fitzhugh Lee, Received of Charles Kerr 11 Nov. 1875?, ADS (Box-folder 1:33)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr from Richland 22 Sept. 1877, ALS (Box-folder 1:34)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr from Richland 9 Oct. 1877, ALS (Box-folder 1:35)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr from Richland 24 Oct. 1877, ALS (Box-folder 1:36)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr from Richland 27 Dec. 1878, ALS (Box-folder 1:37)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Mr. Warfeild from Richland 12 Jan. 1880, ALS (Box-folder 1:38)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr from Spring Bank 4 Jan. 1883, ALS (Box-folder 1:39)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr from Spring Bank 20 Dec. 1883, ALS (Box-folder 1:40)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr from Spring Bank 5 Jan. 1884, ALS (Box-folder 1:41)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Samuel M. Duncan 20 April N.D. (1885?), ALS (Box-folder 1:42)
- Fitzhugh Lee to "My dear General" from Washington, D.C. 17 May 1894, ALS (Box-folder 1:43)
- Fitzhugh Lee to Eliot Danforth from Washington, D.C. 14 April 1898, TLS (Box-folder 1:44)
- George Washington Custis Lee, from Jackson, Miss. 26 Dec. 1862, ALS (Box-folder 1:45)
- George Washington Custis Lee to Thomas F. Balfe from Lexington 10 May 1871, ALS (Box-folder 1:46)
- George Washington Custis Lee, concerning Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh's estate 20 March 1875, DS (Box-folder 1:47)
- George Washington Custis Lee to Harry C. Hines from Lexington 30 Sept. 1876, ALS (Box-folder 1:48)
- George Washington Custis Lee 4 Sept. 1893, Typed letter by his secretary, Thomas E. Marshall from Lexington (Box-folder 1:49)
- Mary Randolph Custis Lee, 9 ALS (Box-folder 1:50)
  - 1850s
    Note: See William Henry Fitzhugh Lee's letter of Feb. 15, 1852 from Baltimore for another ALS by Mary R. Custis Lee which she added on to his letter to his brother Custis at the U.S. Military Academy.
    - Baltimore, to "My dear Abbey" (presumably Abbey Louise Peters (Cook). Says Mary is 15, so that would put this letter at about 1850., 22 August N.D.
    - Arlington, Concerns G. W. P.'s book on Washington which was copyrighted in 1859 and published in 1860. From internal evidence, then, this must have been in the late 1850s, 11 February N.D.
  - 1860s
    - Note on reverse says "Letter received by Abbey L. Cook from Richmond Mrs. Robert E. Lee-Gen. C. S. A. at New York Jan 27th 1865"
    - 12th June 1867 to (Benson J. Lossing) from Lexington (concerning her father's book. (A second edition came out in 1867)
    - May 22 N.D. to "My dear Letty." Internal evidence suggests c. 1868
    - Sunday 29th August N.D. Internal evidence suggests 1869 (S.S. Lee died in 1869). Written from Rockbridge Baths.
    - Note to "My dear Miss Letty" 5th July N.D. from the Hot. 186-?
  - 1870s
    - Sept. 16th 1873 from Lexington
    - Note in the same pocket would appear to be from the 1870s.
- Mary R. Custis Lee 1868?, photograph (Box-folder 1:51)
- Mary Custis Lee (daughter), concerning estate of Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh 20 March 1875, DS (Box-folder 1:52)
- Mildred Lee to Preston Cocke (possibly from Derweat in 1865) N.D., N.P., ALS (Box-folder 1:53)
- Midred Lee, to M. F. Maury, Jr. from Lexington. 4 Jan. 1874, ALS (Box-folder 1:54)
- Midred Lee, to Mary from London 20 Aug. (possibly 1896), ALS (Box-folder 1:55)
- Midred Lee, to Elizabeth Cocke from Lexington 25 Aug. N.D., ALS (Box-folder 1:56)
- Richard Henry Lee to Patrick Henry from Philadelphia 21 Oct. 1778, ALS (Box-folder 1:57)
- Richard Henry Lee to "Dear Sir" (Your Excellency mentioned in text) from Chantilly in Virginia (Box-folder 1:58)
- Richard Henry Lee to Alexander Martin. January 1785, ALS (photocopy) (Box-folder 1:58A)
- Richard Henry Lee, John Houston & Patrick Henry etching dated 1885 (Box-folder 1:59)
- Robert E. Lee, Jr., to Capt. Edmund R. Cocke from Richmond 14 Jan. 1866, ALS (Box-folder 1:60)
- Robert E. Lee, Jr., concerning estate of Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh 20 March 1875, DS (Box-folder 1:61)
- Robert E. Lee, Jr. to E. R. Cocke West Point, Va. 1 March 1913, ALS (Box-folder 1:62)
- Robert E. Lee III, to Edmund R. Cocke from Ravensworth 17 March 1913, ALS (Box-folder 1:63)
- Robert E. Lee, III, to Edmund R. Cocke from Ravensworth 31 Oct. 1914, ALS (Box-folder 1:64)
- William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, to his brother Custis from Baltimore 15 Feb. 1852, ALS (Box-folder 1:65)
  Note: In same letter, ALS from Mary R. Custis Lee to Custis
- William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, concerning estate of Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh 20 March 1875, DS (Box-folder 1:66)
- Photographic scrapbook relating to Robert E. Lee (Box-folder 1:67)
- Custis, George Washington Parke, to Little John from Arlington 23 June 1817, ALS (Box-folder 1:68)
- Custis, George Washington Parke, to Philip R. Tindall from Arlington 12 March 183-?, ALS (Box-folder 1:69)
- Custis, George Washington Parke, to wife and daughter from Arlington 16 Sept. 1839, ALS (Box-folder 1:70)
- Custis, to William Seward from Arlington 15 March 1850, ALS (Box-folder 1:71)
- Custis, George Washington Parke to Henry E. Wise from Arlington 15 Oct. 1850?, ALS (Box-folder 1:72)
- Custis, George Washington Parke to Benson Lossing from Arlington 2 Dec. 1855, ALS (Box-folder 1:73)
- Custis, to Henry Winder? At National Theatre from Arlington N.D., ALS (Box-folder 1:74)
- Custis, Mary Lee Fitzhugh, to Lucretia Stuart? N.D., ALS (Box-folder 1:75)
- P. G. T. Beauregard, reply to "My dear Gov." on note to him May 1861?, ALS. Robert E. Lee signature at top (Box-folder 2:1)
- P. G. T. Beauregard, to "Douce" from St. Louis 2 April 1879, ALS (Box-folder 2:1)
- P. G. T. Beauregard, to Judge Alf. Roman? From New Orleans 25 Oct. 1882, ALS (Box-folder 2:1)
- P. G. T. Beauregard to I. Frank Howe? 22 Dec. 1865, ALS (Box-folder 2:1)
- Thomas N. Burwell, to Col. Edward Carrington from Fincastle 12 June 1810, ALS (Box-folder 2:2)
- Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh 1870-73, printed will and check (Box-folder 2:3)
- Benjamin Hallowell to Robert W. Miller from Sandy Spring, Md. April 14? 1873, ALS (Box-folder 2:4)
- 2 ALS to Benjamin Hallowell relative to the subject in his ALS (Box-folder 2:4)
  19 April 1851 from D. I. Markey from Frederick, Md.
  17 April 1851 from Ayers from Harrisburg, Pa.
- D. H. Hill to Honorable John W. Ellis from Yorktown, Va. 16 June 1861, ALS (Box-folder 2:5)
- Jed Hotchkiss, to his wife from London 30 Jan. 1873, ALS (Box-folder 2:6)
- Gen. Edward Johnson, from Camp Alleghany 17 Jan. 1862 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Gen. Edward Johnson, from Camp Alleghany 5 Aug. 1861 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Gen. J. E. Johnston, 5 ALS (Box-folder 2:9)
  8 Sept. 1841 to "Captain" from Buffalo
  27 May 1862 to Major General Jackson from Johnston's Northern Va. Headquarters
  4 Feb. 1866 to Major Gen. Wilson from Richmond
  30 July 1870 to J. L. Cabell, M. D. from Sweet Chalybeate Springs
  4? Dec. 1874 to Col. C. H. Andrews from Savannah
- Gen. J. E. Johnston In Memoriam(printed) by A. T. Porter 1891 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Margaret Junkin, 2 ALS and as M. J. Preston, 1 TLS (Box-folder 2:11)
  14 Jan. N.D. to Mr. Sartain from Lexington
  12? Feb. 1852 to Mr. Sartain from Lexington
  20 Feb. N.D. To H.E. Peck from Lexington
- William Penn McKune 15 Sept. 1850, AMs (Box-folder 2:12)
  "For Sarah Ann
- "Nellie", from Scotland 30 Aug. 1874, ALS (Box-folder 2:13)
- E. F. Paxton to S. I. Campbell from camp 27 April 1863, ALS (Box-folder 2:14)
- Frank Preston 8 July 1797, ALS (Box-folder 2:15)
- Rockbridge County Election Record 1860 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Gen. Winfield Scott and others, battle orders to Commander/Capt. Dahlgren 1861 and N.D. (Box-folder 2:17)